Good afternoon everybody.
Today's דף daf is ק"ח. kuf chet. We're continuing in פרק חלק.
perek chelek. מיכל Michal took us yesterday just to right before the
expunged part of the גמרא Gemara on ק"ז עמוד ב, kuf zayin
amud bet, which is the גמרא Gemara is wrapping up the people
that don't have a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba, and it
mentions גיחזי. Geichazi. It's sort of interestingly, by the way, when it
gets to גיחזי, Geichazi, it doesn't do the normal thing דרש darshaning
the name, talking about what פסוק pasuk we know he doesn't have
a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba, right? It more sort of
just jumps right into the whole story that
אלישע Elisha tried to get him to do תשובה teshuva and then
he refused to do תשובה teshuva and so on. So it's really
interesting, like it says the weakest technicals
sort of textual support
there, but there we introduce the idea that גיחזי's Geichazi response to
אלישע Elisha was כך מקובלני מבית אבא, kach mekublani mibeit ava, anybody
who חוטא ומחטיא את הרבים אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה. choteh u'machti
et harabbim ein maspikin beyado la'asot teshuva. Now even if אין מספיקין
בידו לעשות תשובה ein maspikin beyado la'asot teshuva doesn't mean not to
have a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba, but anyway, and then
it had to figure out how was he מחטיא את הרבים, machti
et harabbim, like the whole story he did with נעמן Naaman wasn't
being מחטיא, machti, he didn't cause the masses to sin. So it
spoke about being involved with the golden calves there that ירבעם Yerovam
did, or interesting some things that seem obviously it's bad, but it
wouldn't think like it set you out of עולם הבא olam haba
that he kept the students away from אלישע. Elisha. Anyway, so that
scene now is going to repeat itself because we
have רבנן דקמו בפתח השער, rabbanan d’kamu bepetach hash’ar, so אמר רבי
יוחנן גיחזי ושלושה בניו amar Rabbi Yochanan Geichazi ushloshah banav. and יהושע
בן פרחיה. Yehoshua ben Perachia. So there was a case because the
גמרא Gemara earlier had said, right, one minute, where
was
it? Okay, right, because it said, if you look at the asterisk
about ten lines from the wide lines, it says תנו רבנן לעולם
תהא שמאל דוחה וימין מקרבת, tanu rabbanan leolam tehei semol docheh veyamin
mekarevet, the left should always
be pushing away and the right should be drawing near. So even
when you have to give a person מוסר mussar ultimately you should
be getting them closer. Okay, and it said לא כאלישע שדחפו לגיחזי
בשתי ידיו, lo k'Elisha shedachfo l'Geichazi bishtei yadav, not like אלישע Elisha
who pushed גיחזי Geichazi away with two hands. And then the missing
line
was ולא כיהושע בן פרחיה שדחפו לישו הנוצרי בשתי ידיו, velo k'Yehoshua
ben Perachia shedachfo l'Yeishu HaNozri bishtei yadav, and not like יהושע בן
פרחיה Yehoshua ben Perachia that pushed away Jesus of Nazareth with two
hands. And then מיכל Michal read for us the other day the
whole story about גיחזי, Geichazi, right, and how he pushed him away
with two hands, and then the whole thing about the שמונה שרצים
shemonah shratzim or whatever, now צרעת נעמן תדבק בך. tzaraat Naaman tidbak
becha. Okay, so now going back to where we left off, וארבעה
אנשים היו מצורעים פתח השער, v’arba'ah anashim hayu metzoraim petach hash’ar, אמר
רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan גיחזי ושלושה בניו. Geichazi ushloshah banav This
was now the צרעת tzaraat of גיחזי. Geichazi. So that's the story
about how אלישע Elisha pushed גיחזי Geichazi away with two hands. And
now we pick up with the part that has been taken out.
So if you have it great, if not you'll listen. I don't
know what's going on with my phone today. תניא. tanya. So here
is the missing part.
ויהושע בן פרחיה מאי היא, v'Yehoshua ben Perachia mai hi, what's the
story with יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Perachia
that parallels the story of אלישע Elisha and גיחזי? Geichazi? כדקטלינו ינאי
מלכא לרבנן, kidekatlinu Yannai Malka l'rabbanan, when ינאי Yannai the king killed
all of the rabbis, אזל רבי יהושע בן פרחיה וישו לאלכסנדריא
של מצרים, azal Rabbi Yehoshua ben Perachia v'Yeishu l'Alexandria shel Mitzrayim, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Perachia and ישו Yeishu went to Alexandria because according to
this ישו Yeishu Jesus was his student. כי הוה שלמא, ki hava
shalma, then when there was peace again in the Land of Israel,
שלח ליה שמעון בן שטח shelach lei Shimon ben Shatach to יהושע
בן פרחיה, Yehoshua ben Perachia, מירושלים עיר הקודש לכי אלכסנדריא של מצרים
אחותי בעלי שרוי בתוכך ואני יושב שומם, miyerushalayim ir hakodesh lichi alexandria
shel mitzrayim achoti ba'ali sharuy betochech va'ani yoshev shomem, from me Jerusalem
the holy city to
you Alexandria of Egypt, my sister, my
husband is dwelling amongst
you and I am here
desolate. So I Jerusalem am waiting for my husband, the meaning he's
telling יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Perachia it's safe to come back.
קם אתא, kam ata, so יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Perachia got
up and started going back. איתרמי ליה ההוא אושפיזא, itrami lei hahu
ushpiza, he came to a certain inn. עבדו ליה יקרא טובא, avdu
lei yakira tuva, they did for him a lot of very a
great honor. אמר כמה יפה אכסניא זו, amar kamah yafa aksanya zo,
how great is this innkeeper, this female innkeeper?
Or could it also just mean the inn itself?
Yeah, I think it can. Anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, so ישו
Yeishu said to him, רבי עיניה טרוטות, Rebbi eineiha terutot, but רבי,
Rebbi, her eyes are like slanted. אמר ליה רשע בכך אתה עוסק,
amar lei rasha bechach ata osek, wicked one, is that what you're
busy with? That's what you're paying attention to, her looks? I'm talking
about how kind she was, how welcoming she was. So אפיק ארבע
מאה שופורי דצפורי ושמתיה, afik arba meah shofurei ditzporei vashamteih, took out
400 shofars and he put him into חרם, cherem, which is a
pretty radical response. I don't know.
ושמתיה, vashamteih, I have no idea. אתא לקמיה כמה זימנין, ata lekameih
kama zimnin, right, because it's different at least in the אלישע וגיחזי
Elisha veGeichazi story, his initial reaction was somewhat justified, I mean even
there you could say אלישע Elisha a little bit overreacted, I don't
know, you know, צרעת tzaraat whatever, so, but alright anyway that people
you know when your students are basically not following after you know
your sort of מידות middot and they're one case drawn after material
here drawn after sort of more you know physical sexual or whatever
so maybe he felt it also reflected poorly on him I don't
know he got very it clearly was I don't know what to
tell you okay was it clear it was a very strong overreaction
anyway אתא לקמיה כמה זימנין ata lekameih kama zimnin
so ישו Yeshu returned to him many times and אמר ליה קבלן
amar lei kablan so please re-accept me back I want to do
תשובה teshuvah ולא הוה קא משגח ביה velo hava ka mashgach beih
didn't pay attention to him this was the ימין דוחה yamin docah
but actually both hands were דוחה docah דוחה בשתי ידיים docah bishtei
yadayim right so יומא חד yoma chad one day הוה קא קרי
קריאת שמע hava ka kari kariat shema he
so so רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Perachiah was reading
קריאת שמע kariat shema
אתא לקמיה ata lekameih so ישו Yeshu came to him סבר לקבוליה
savar lekabuleih so finally רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Perachiah
said you know what it's enough I'm going to accept him back
אחוי ליה בידיה achvei lei bideih so he signaled with his hand
like wait a minute הוא סבר מידחא דחי ליה hu savar midadcha
dachi lei he saw him signaling and he thought it was like
get out of here okay אזל azal so that was it that
was the final straw אזל זקף לבינתא azal zakaf levinta he he
put up a a brick והשתחוה לה vehishtachavah lah and bowed down
to it so that's why it doesn't exactly fit the ישו Yeshu
story bowing down to some brick anyway אמר ליה הדר בך amar
lei hadar bach and then רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rebbi Yehoshua ben
Perachiah then he started coming after him and said do תשובה teshuvah
אמר ליה amar lei same end as the אלישע וגיחזי Elisha veGeichazi
story כך מקובלני ממך kach mekublani mimcha this is my tradition from
you כל החוטא ומחטיא את הרבים kol hachote umachati et harabim you
don't get אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה ein maspikin beyado laasot teshuvah
presumably the putting up of the brick was drawing other people after
him אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה ein maspikin beyado laasot teshuvah okay
did you don't allow him and אמר מר amar mar and the
and the master said ישו הנוצרי Yeshu HaNotzri כישף והסית והדיח את
ישראל kishaf vehisit vehidich et Yisrael so that's the מחטיא את הרבים
machati et harabim he did witchcraft and he seduced and he pushed
the Jewish people away now the interesting point about this כישף והסית
kishaf vehisit I mean
הסית hesit could be in an עבודה זרה avodah zarah context but
it's not clearly עבודה זרה avodah zarah as opposed to the previous
story about the brick and you know part of the whole question
is how do you deal from a from a perspective of Jewish
faith with all of the stories about all the stuff that Jesus
did in the gospels right you know he made whatever the fishes
and the loaves and the water and all the stuff right so
you could just say oh whatever you know it's all just made
up it's all nonsense or whatever but you know another way of
dealing with this well maybe he was a magician that's how he
was able to do it right so the כישף kishaf is interesting
because the כישף והסית kishaf vehisit fits within the narrative of the
gospels right you're not claiming that he's an עובד עבודה זרה oved
avodah zarah he's just somebody that is seducing the people away from
the traditional rabbinic path doing it through through sort of miracles which
could be כישף kishaf you know which could be sort of you
know magic or whatever it is so that anyway sort of at
least fits a way of trying to position him within those you
know a rabbinic way of positioning within those stories the problem of
course is that it cause you know it seems unquestionable who it's
referring to ישו הנוצרי Yeshu HaNotzri but the dating doesn't work because
ינאי Yannai and רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Perachiah whatever
they were like a hundred years earlier so which doesn't mean I
mean that's what we were saying at the end of the other
day which doesn't mean that that wasn't in the rabbinic mind they
weren't talking about Jesus you know this is just this is a
story this is not historical you know what I mean it means
that that's not this not this not historically you know what you
know historically this is not an accurate story that's what it means
okay because the dates don't work but it doesn't mean that that
doesn't it isn't who the rabbis were thinking about when they were
telling this story yes
just like the fact that
if you say afterwards it was censored so it can be in
some rabbinic thoughts like maybe it's not the same king right it's
not the same rabbi
right that could be too maybe they wanted to tell the story
but then they say ישו הנוצרי Yeshu HaNotzri so so ישו Yeshu
yes
but it was רבים rabim because the people were in danger
right maybe yeah i
mean who knows so then why would why would they be thinking
about it this way with the ינאי ורבי שמעון בן שטח Yannai
veRebbi Shimon ben Shetach as opposed to more historically and also
meaning just because no meaning I don't I
mean it could just be they weren't you know they weren't historians
like they didn't like you know they knew these stories that they
were getting from their surroundings about Jesus or whatever you know did
they actually go and i mean the problem is that they all
like like look the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was around when when
Jesus was around so you can't position it as it's obviously after
חורבן הבית churban habayit right I mean the story is though in
the gospels there are stories with him and i think רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel but but
look you know if you're not reading the New Testament and you're
not doing close reading and historical placing you just know yeah there
was this Jesus at the end of the period of the בית
שני Bayit Sheini so you know it's historical memory i don't think
that it means you know.
I think it was something with the שמאל
דוחה וימין מקרבת Smol Docheh VeYamin Mekareves and how
close he was to the rabbis and inside the people and this
made it out some way to save that situation and yet they
did this
right דוחה
בשתי ידים Docheh Bishtei Yadayim and they
didn't.
Right.
Could be. I mean I also think that the part we want
to pay attention to was the Alexandria because, you know, this by
having him running away, having him with in as Michal was saying
like with as a rabbinic student similar to the גיחזי Geichazi and
the אלישע, Elisha, you know, you're close and then you go astray,
right, so where did he learn the witchcraft to mislead the people?
Oh, he went to Alexandria and because they were spending time in
Alexandria, that, you know, all the witchcraft in Egypt. So I think
that might be a reason to position him with what's a good
rabbi doing in Alexandria, you know, it helps so this historical framing
helps position that. But anyway, let's keep on going. So as opposed
to again, notice by the way there were three options, right, you
could have four options. You could have both hands being מקרב. Mekarev.
You could have שמאל דוחה וימין מקרבת, Smol Docheh VeYamin Mekareves, which
is like a little מוסר Musar but ultimately pulling the person back.
You could have, you know, the you would see the flip of
that is, you know, ימין דוחה ושמאל מקרבת, Yamin Docheh VeSmol Mekareves,
a little harsh on the מוסר Musar but a little bit pulling
back. But the context of the גמרא Gemara is, you know, don't
go don't go דוחה בשתי ידים, Docheh Bishtei Yadayim, right? So אלישע
Elisha and, you know, this story of רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Perachyah wasn't enough that they weren't שמאל דוחה וימין מקרבת,
Smol Docheh VeYamin Mekareves, they weren't even ימין דוחה ושמאל מקרבת, Yamin
Docheh VeSmol Mekareves, they were דוחה בשתי ידים. Docheh Bishtei Yadayim. All
right. And with that in mind the גמרא Gemara now wraps up
the discussion, תניא Tanya we taught, אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar יצר תינוק ואשה Yetzer Tinok VeIshah similarly, however,
when it comes to your יצר הרע, Yetzer Hara, which normally means
your sexual desire,
dealing with kids and dealing with women. I'm just reading the גמרא.
Gemara. Obviously this does not afford to our contemporary sensibilities or, you
know, morality ethics around these issues, תהא שמאל דוחה וימין מקרבת. Tehei
Smol Docheh VeYamin Mekareves. Your left should push away and your right
should draw close. Now what does that mean with your יצר הרע
Yetzer Hara sexual desire? So, you know, it's interesting because this actually
comes up if you read stuff, you know, about how much there
is sadly in certain segments of the חרדי Charedi and חסידי Chassidi
communities even till today talking about like ideally, you know, it's a
little bit in רמב"ם Rambam about how ideally you should try, you
know, you should try to actually have like as little marital sex
as possible. Okay. And ultimately not even like, you know, רמב"ם Rambam
sort of says, you know, speaks about like like
ideally if you get your wife to be מוחל Mochel so that
you don't have to have sex like that would be even something
of an ideal so that after you've been יוצא פרו ורבו Yotzei
Peru Urevu you spend your time learning תורה. Torah. But you know
in some חסידי Chassidi literature or whatever or more חרדי Charedi literature,
you know, it also talks about like, you know, I mean some
not, some actually try to acknowledges that like there's profound human and
marital and, you know, interpersonal issues here, but some talk about this
ascetic ideal and not even trying to get pleasure, trying to minimize
it. So of course that is not healthy. Okay. And the גמרא
Gemara here while obviously it doesn't want somebody to become a בעל
תאוה Baal Taavah and live a life that's about pursuing, you know,
sensual pleasures, right, it understands that A, God made us with these
desires so we have to give them an outlet and B, there's
actual parts about marital harmony and discord and finding satisfaction within marriage.
So if you look at רש"י Rashi by יצר, Yetzer, right, רש"י
Rashi says תאוותו אם ירחיקנה ממנו לגמרי ימנע ישובו של עולם, Taavato
Im Yarchikennah Mimenu Legamrei Yimna Yishuvo Shel Olam, which speaks not so
much to the marital accord and relationship of husband and wife and
the wife's pleasure but speaks about having kids, okay, if you try
to push it away too much you won't have kids. ואם יקרבנה
לגמרי יבא לידי איסור שאינו יכול לכבוש יצרו מדבר עבירה. VeIm Yekarvenah
Legamrei Yavo Lidei Issur SheEino Yachol Lichbosh Yitzro Midvar Aveirah. And if
you indulge in it too much then you're going to be taken
away from it, right, like the גמרא Gemara the other day with
דוד המלך David HaMelech like יצר קטן יש באדם, Yetzer Katan Yesh
BaAdam, right, so the גמרא Gemara is trying to strike that balance.
אבר קטן, Eiver Katan, sorry, אבר קטן, Eiver Katan, thank you. But
you know, but I would say more than just רש"י, Rashi, right,
if you push it away too much besides you won't have kids,
right, and besides what again we're it's obviously the גמרא Gemara is
speaking to the man, besides that it might mean that your wife
won't be happy and whatever and all those things, but, you know,
if we try to deny parts of our fundamental parts of of
who we are, then they find outlets elsewhere. It could also, you
know, denying it too much could also lead to, you know, you
know, we've had these terrible stories of sexual downfall, like, you know,
right before. So that's the issue about the יצר. Yetzer. So what's
about the תינוק ואשה? Tinok VeIshah?
So the רש"י Rashi says here דעתן קלה ואם תרחיקם יטרדו מן
העולם. Daatan Kallah VeIm Tarchikem Yitardu Min HaOlam. So it sounds like
he's reading that more along the lines of the אלישע Elisha story
or the גיחזי Geichazi story, you know, like when you have to
like give your kid like you have to punish them, you know,
he goes off the road, you know, so okay, you you punish
them, but don't be too harsh cause then he's going to rebel
or whatever, you know, on the other hand, don't don't not punish
them. And they need a little מוסר musar *mussar*, so it's שמאל
דוחה וימין מקרבת *smol docha viyamin mekarevet*, and sort of seems to
read the issue here with the wife as well, like not in
the sexual context, right, but in general like, you know, when the
husband has to correct his wife or his wife's wrong behavior seems
to be the way like רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is reading. You could
read the wife issue in the sexual context as well, that like
if the wife is and then gets back, I think that's the
way the ראב"ד *Raavad* reads it in בעלי הנפש *Baalei HaNefesh*. That
there's one, the man dealing with his own, you know, sexual desires,
that's the יצר *yetzer*, and the other is like responding to his
wife's sexual desires. So it's sort of the two sides of the
coin but it's ultimately the same about you have to, it's interesting,
right? It's only שמאל דוחה *smol docheh*, it's not ימין דוחה *yamin
docheh*. Ultimately you have to be more ימין מקרב *yamin mekarev* because
recognizing again the complexity of that reality. Did you want to say
something, Michal?
And you also referred to it that ימין *yamin* is חסד *chesed*
and שמאל *smol* is דין din. *din*.
I did not, but that's a good point. ימין *yamin* is חסד
*chesed* and שמאל *smol* is דין *din*. And while we're at it,
I should also mention Rabbi Weiss loves quoting the line which says
that if you're pushing away with your left and pulling with your
right, if you're doing both at the same time, then you're turning
somebody around, you're like reorienting, helping give the person a new perspective,
you're reorienting them. So that's why. Anyway, okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this: תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan, *Tanna Rabbanan*, ג'
חלאים חלה אלישע *Gimmel cholaim chala Elisha*. He had three illnesses. אחד
שגירה דובים בתינוקות *Echad she-girah dubim b'tinokot*, one is when he caused
the bears to go attack the kids who were making fun of
him. ואחד שדחפו לגיחזי בשתי ידים *V'echad she-dachfo l'Geichazi b'shteiy yadayim*, one
that he was punished, though we don't see that in the פסוק
pasuk. *pasuk*. פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* says he pushed away גיחזי *Geichazi* with
two hands. ואחד שמת בו *V'echad she-meis bo*, the one that ultimately
led to his death, שנאמר ואלישע חלה את חליו אשר ימות בו
Shene'emar v'elisha chala et chalyo asher yamut bo, *shene'emar v'Elisha chala es
cholyo asher yamut bo*. So that's three: חלה *chala*, חליו *cholyo*, and
the one that he ultimately would die by. עד אברהם לא היה
זקנה ziknah, *Ad Avraham lo hayah ziknah*. Until אברהם *Avraham*, nobody got
old. I mean they died, but they looked like they were in
their prime of youth up to the day they died. כל דחזי
לאברהם אמר יצחק *Kol dechazi l'Avraham amar Yitzchak*. כל דחזי ליצחק אמר
אברהם *Kol dechazi l'Yitzchak amar Avraham*. Everybody thought אברהם *Avraham* and יצחק
*Yitzchak* looked the same, but you know, it's such one thing to
have your kid look like you, which is the רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
on אברהם הוליד את יצחק *Avraham holid es Yitzchak*. But eventually the
father grows old, you know, there's a, there's an age disparity and
you're obviously, you know, you see that they look similar, but you
see the difference. But here if you're in the prime of your
youth, they look the exact same. So בעי אברהם רחמי *ba'ei Avraham
rachamei*, so אברהם *Avraham* prayed דהויא ליה זקנה *d'leihavei lei ziknah*, that
he should actually have the effects of old age, שנאמר shene'emar ואברהם
זקן zaken בא בימים *shene'emar v'Avraham zaken ba bayamim*. And what they're
picking up on is that it never says prior to this verse
that anybody grew old, that it's really the first verse in the
תורה *Torah* where it says that somebody grew old. Okay, so you
should show your years on you, you know, as a society should
relate. Now of course that's good in a society that honors its
elderly, right, you know, and relate to the wisdom and the experience
of older people and so on. And, you know, it's interesting, right?
Some people sort of say, oh, young at heart, and somebody's like,
what? That's so offensive to old people. What, if you're not a
young at heart, like you're all withered up or whatever? Like, you
know, some people like, like, I own my age, you know, I
say, you know, I'm not a kid anymore. So it's interesting, like
that desire that to show that your age should show, you know,
and again, some in, in some, in many I think ancient societies
you have it, and now we have this whole culture of youth
and everybody wants to get like, like what's her name?
What's her name? The actress?
Oh, I can't think of her name. Anyway, she was married to
the owner of
the, of the football team. Nobody knows who I'm talking about. Anyway,
Jane Fonda. Jane Fonda. So she's like eighty. She's like eighty. She
looks fifty. She's had like ten facelifts. I mean she looks amazing.
Okay, but like, you know, but we, we live in a different
culture, right? But if you, if you don't have a culture of
youth and of the, you know, that respect and honoring the wisdom,
the experience, so people, you know, and even till this day, whatever,
some people really, you know, want to own their, their age. Okay,
so that's אברהם *Avraham*. עד יעקב לא היה חולשא chulsha, *Ad Yaakov
lo hayah chusha*. Before יעקב *Yaakov*, nobody got sick. They just dropped
dead when their clock expired. Okay, so בעי רחמי והוה חולשא *ba'ei
rachamei v'havah chusha*. So יעקב *Yaakov* prayed that there should be illness
leading up to death, שנאמר shene'emar, ויאמר ליוסף הנה אביך חולה *shene'emar
v'yomar l'Yosef hinei avicha choleh*. And as רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, because
that gives everybody time to prepare, right? It allows for the transition
out of the world, to mentally prepare for the person who's going
to die, for the family, you know, and it's, you know, and
that's the whole story there. He draws them close, he gives them
a ברכה bracha, *bracha*, etc. Okay,
so like, right, because we don't have, I mean אברהם *Avraham* gives
יצחק *Yitzchak* a ברכה *bracha*, right? And יצחק *Yitzchak* gives יעקב *Yaakov*,
but not on their deathbed, right? They just, you know, so I
mean although by יצחק *Yitzchak* it's
ויהי כי זקן יצחק ותכהין
עיניו מראות *vayehi ki zaken Yitzchak vatechleina einav m're'os*, לא ידעתי יום
מותי *lo yadati yom mosi*, which means that there was some sense
but I guess the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is reading it
is some sense based on the age. Right. There's not yet the
physical expression of it. Well, most people die around 120, so I'll
probably die sometime soon, you know. But right, so anyway, which also
by the way today is a very mixed blessing because of the
way we, you know, extend the dying period, you know, with artificial
means and just makes things so complicated for, you know, for families
and for the person or whatever. Anyway, okay. So,
okay, ויאמר ליוסף הנה אביך חולה. עדי אלישע לא הוה איניש חליש
דמתפח. Adei elisha lo hava inish chalish d'mitpach. Before Elisha, nobody ever
got sick and then recovered. Sickness always meant it was you were
about you were going to die. This was the process of death.
Okay, ואתא אלישע בעא רחמי ואתפח. Va'ata elisha ba'a rachamei v'itpach. שנאמר
Shene'emar, ואלישע חלה את חליו אשר ימות בו, which means prior he
got sick and he didn't die by it. So that you understand,
of course that doesn't need any explanation why somebody's getting sick they
want to survive. But what it also means is that it also
gives God the opportunity if until then sickness only just leads to
death, then God doesn't have the opportunity to send people like, you
know, mini-punishments or to give people wake-up calls like the story before
about חזקיה, Chizkiyah, right? Or about the other, right, you know, if
you're getting sick and then you're afraid you're going to die and
then you have to pray because that's true a lot in תנ"ך
Tanakh when it talks about people getting sick, the sense is that
they're afraid they're going to die, right? And then maybe they do
תשובה teshuvah and then God reverses it. Okay, and you don't hear
that they just had like a cold, okay? They had a high
fever and by the way, you know, just prior to a hundred,
hundred, you know, years ago or so, right, any normal fever was
a concern of death, right? You didn't know how things were going
to develop. Okay, we finally move on to the next משנה. Mishnah.
We got the list of the people that don't have a חלק
לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. And in this משנה, Mishnah, we continue
to speak about more sort of not individuals but broad classes of
people. And what we also introduce is a difference between a portion
in the world to come and whether somebody's going to be resurrected
for יום הדין, Yom HaDin, whether they're חיים. chayim. So again, the
general sense is, you know, משיח Mashiach will come, there'll be a
תחיית המתים. techiyat hameitim. Everybody will be resurrected. The righteous ones will
stay, will get עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, maybe God will destroy the
world and rebuild it and they'll float in the air or who
knows where they'll be hanging out till we're sort of get the
עולם הבא Olam HaBa ready. Okay, and the and the רשעים reshaim
will go back to גיהנום Gehennom and get, you know, and live
their life in perdition. So אין לו חלק לעולם הבא Ein lo
chelek l'olam haba presumably means they're resurrected, but then at the day
of judgment they're not going to stick around for עולם הבא. Olam
HaBa. Now we're going to see some people who don't even get
resurrected.
Okay, yeah, one thing from before, you know, but things can't be
underestimated how the גמרא Gemara reframes things and we may be taking
this big negative and so, you know, positive things are even worthy
to pray for, like זקנה, חולשא, ייסורין.
yissurin. Right, I appreciate that. Right, right, meaning, exactly, I appreciate that.
You're right. Like, I mean, if we the our normal response, you
know, it's not just in modern days we don't val-, you know,
we have a youth culture, right, even when the גמרא Gemara was
being written clearly, you know, there's plenty of people didn't like, I
assume, right, there's a lot of like problems that go along with
old age and that the גמרא Gemara is actually making a real
radical sort of reframing of those. Thank you, I appreciate that. Okay,
so let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. דור המבול אין
להם חלק לעולם הבא. Dor HaMabul ein lahem chelek l'olam haba. The
generation of the flood has no portion in the world to come.
ואינם עומדים בדין. v'einam omdim b'din. Not only that, they don't even
get resurrected. Okay, שנאמר Shene'emar, as it says, לא ידון רוחי באדם
לעולם, lo yadon ruchi b'adam l'olam, that my spirit will not dwell
or judge among people. לא דין ולא רוח. Lo din v'lo ruach.
They won't have the רוח, ruach, their souls won't live for עולם
הבא, Olam HaBa, לא דין, lo din, but they won't even stand
for judgment, which is seen as worse. You don't even deserve to
have your case heard. Okay, you're so much out of the פרשה.
parsha. All right. Presumably, now if you're going
to go to גיהנום Gehennom anyway, what's
the purpose of being judged? Like, so yeah, so that's never like
fully explained but again, I guess the point is is that, you
know, at least you feel like your life is worth being obsessed
to determine, right, it's worth, you know, something is like dismissed doesn't
even get a hearing in court. Okay, so it's a worse punishment.
I anyway, I don't know.
Does actually as a soul doing worse not being judged?
I have no idea.
We have things we have no idea.
Exactly, exactly, exactly. So let's keep on moving. Exactly. But what I
would say is like why is it because דור המבול Dor HaMabul
were bigger sinners than some of the previous or was it because
the collective nature of their sin, that their sin caused the world
to be destroyed? Like why is it that these the ones that
don't even get aren't even עומד לדין? omed l'din? It's an interesting
question what makes it worse. Okay. דור הפלגה אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא. Dor HaPalaga ein lahem chelek l'olam haba. The generation of the
dispersion, the מגדל בבל. Migdal Bavel. Okay, but it doesn't say that
they're not עומד בדין. omed b'din. Excuse me, אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא, ein lahem chelek l'olam haba, but it doesn't say they're not
עומד בדין. omed b'din. שנאמר ויפץ ה' אותם משם על פני כל
הארץ. shene'emar vayafetz Hashem otam misham al pnei kol ha'aretz. ויפץ ה'
אותם Vayafetz Hashem otam בעולם הזה. ba'olam hazeh. ומשם הפיצם ה' Umisham
hepitzam Hashem from there he scattered them לעולם הבא. l'olam haba. אנשי
סדום אין להם חלק לעולם הבא. Anshei Sedom ein lahem chelek l'olam
haba.
What did they do so bad in דור הפלגה? Dor HaPalaga?
Oh, about well, what did God view so bad? I mean, I
don't know. That's trying to figure out the narrative there itself. It's
not clear what was so terrible about what they did. Okay. אנשי
סדום אין להם חלק לעולם הבא. Anshei Sedom ein lahem chelek l'olam
haba. The people of סדום Sedom don't have a portion in the
world to come, שנאמר ואנשי סדום רעים וחטאים לה' מאד. shene'emar v'anshei
sedom ra'im v'chatta'im l'Hashem me'od. רעים בעולם הזה וחטאים לעולם הבא. Ra'im
ba'olam hazeh v'chatta'im l'olam haba. אבל עומדים בדין. Aval omdim b'din. They
do stand the דין. רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah אומר omer אלו ואלו
אין עומדים בדין. elu v'elu ein omdim b'din. Nope, I'm sorry. Both
דור הפלגה Dor HaPalaga and סדום Sedom are not עומד בדין. omed
b'din. שנאמר על כן לא יקומו רשעים במשפט. shene'emar al ken lo
yakumu reshaim bamishpat. The wicked will not stand in judgment. ורשעים v'reshaim
וחטאים בעדת צדיקים v'chata'im ba'adat tzadikim and the sinners in the community
of the righteous. על כן לא יקומו רשעים במשפט, Al ken lo
yakumu risha'im bamishpat, זה דור המבול, zeh Dor HaMabul, וחטאים בעדת צדיקים,
v'chata'im ba'adat tzadikim, אלו אנשי סדום. elu anshei Sdom. By the way,
he doesn't argue with דור הפלגה. Dor HaPlagah. Maybe because of Michael's
point, like, okay, it's not even clear what big their sin was.
Okay, but he says fine, דור הפלגה Dor HaPlagah maybe is עומד
בדין, omed badin, but אנשי סדום anshei Sdom is not עומד בדין.
omed badin. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him,
אינם עומדים בעדת צדיקים. einam omdim ba'adat tzadikim. No, the רשעים, risha'im,
the two parts of the פסוק. pasuk לא יקומו רשעים במשפט, Lo
yakumu risha'im bamishpat, the fully רשעים, risha'im, the דור המבול Dor HaMabul
don't even get their case in court. They're not standing in judgment.
But the חטאים, chata'im, sinners, are not the same as wicked people.
Okay, so the חטאים, chata'im, they're not standing with the צדיקים, tzadikim,
but that doesn't mean that they're not getting their day in court,
they're not getting judged. Okay? Okay. And notice the חטאים chata'im works
very good, 'cause that's what it says by אנשי סדום, anshei Sdom,
right? אנשי סדום רעים וחטאים. Anshei Sdom ra'im v'chata'im.
Okay? So they said back to him, וחטאים v'chata'im are אינם עומדים
בעדת צדיקים. einam omdim ba'adat tzadikim. They don't get to be with
the righteous. אבל עומדים בעדת רשעים, Aval omdim ba'adat risha'im, they get
to be amongst the wicked. They at least are עומד בדין. omed
badin. So the רשעים risha'im are not עומד בדין, omed badin, that's
דור המבול, Dor HaMabul, but the חטאים chata'im are עומד. omed. They're
just going to be judged and found guilty. Okay, so now there's
a question about this next line. מרגלים אין להם חלק לעולם הבא,
Meraglim ein lahem chelek l'olam haba, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, וימותו האנשים מוציאי דבת
הארץ רעה במגפה לפני השם, vayumutu ha'anashim motzi'ei dibat ha'aretz ra'ah bamagefah
lifnei Hashem, וימותו vayumutu בעולם הזה, ba'olam hazeh, במגפה bamagefah לעולם הבא.
l'olam haba. So that's the מרגלים, meraglim, but the reason it's taken
out is because the next line makes the previous one moot. דור
המדבר אין להם חלק לעולם הבא, Dor HaMidbar ein lahem chelek l'olam
haba, the generation of the whole that whole generation that lived in
the 40 years of the wilderness. Okay, which obviously includes the
מרגלים. meraglim. ואינם עומדים בדין, v'einam omdim badin, and even worse than
that previous line of the מרגלים, meraglim, which is why that line
was taken out, because they don't even get עומד בדין. omed badin.
Now that's really very hard to understand, right? I mean, okay, fine,
they had the whole sin with the מרגלים meraglim or whatever, but
it's, I mean, especially look, if you read the stories, there's nothing
that looks so righteous about the people. I mean, okay, except for
that initial faith that they had of leaving מצרים, Mitzrayim, but you
know, also to some degree they didn't have the faith initially and
what were their alternatives and so on. Anyway, but through חז"ל's Chazal
eyes, right, they often the דור המדבר Dor HaMidbar is described in
the as this great צדיקים tzadikim and righteous and so on. And
even if they weren't, you know, okay, they were previous slaves or
whatever, like why אינם עומדים בדין? ein omdim badin? Like really? Like
that's how bad they are? So again, maybe these אינם עומדים בדין
ein omdim badin have something to do with the collective nature of
it and the consequence of it, right? The consequence of not of
having lost the opportunity to go into the land of Israel and
so on. It's not clear to me, you know, it seems like
a very overly harsh judgment here.
שנאמר, she'ne'emar, במדבר הזה יתמו ושם ימותו. bamidbar hazeh yitamu v'sham yamutu.
So I don't get how יתמו ושם ימותו yitamu v'sham yamutu means
אינם עומדים בדין. ein omdim badin. It means אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא ein lahem chelek l'olam haba maybe. דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Reb
Akiva. רבי אליעזר אומר, Reb Eliezer omer, עליהם הוא אומר, alehem hu
omer, so
Reb Eliezer says,
what do you mean, they were righteous. אספו לי
חסידי, Isfu li chasidai, gather for Me My righteous ones, כורתי בריתי
עלי זבח, kortei briti alei zavach, the ones who make My covenant
over the sacrifice. They are, how could you say that? So he's
not just saying they're עומדים בדין, omdim badin, completely different view. Okay.
עדת קרח אינה עתידה לעלות, Adat Korach einah atidah la'alot, the congregation
of Korach. So since they're דור המדבר, Dor HaMidbar, they're not going
to have עולם הבא olam haba either. But besides which, they're like
in a little different state because they are still alive down in
the depths. As opposed to everybody else who died, they're not going
to be resurrected. But what about them? They're living and they're still
living down there in the netherworld somewhere. Eternally alive? Yeah. And they're
not going to come back up. שנאמר, She'ne'emar ותכס עליהם הארץ vatichas
alehem ha'aretz בעולם הזה, ba'olam hazeh, ויאבדו מתוך הקהל vayovdu mitoch hakahal
לעולם הבא. l'olam haba. דברי רבי עקיבא. Divrei Reb Akiva. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Reb Eliezer omer, עליהם הוא אומר, alehem hu omer, השם ממית
ומחיה מוריד שאול ויעל. Hashem memit umchayeh morid sheol vaya'al. So the
Reb Eliezer who says that the whole דור המדבר Dor HaMidbar will
be עומד בדין omed badin and probably get עולם הבא, olam haba,
okay, so קרח Korach isn't going to get עולם הבא, olam haba,
but at least they're going to be עומד בדין. omed badin. God
brings them down and God will bring them up. Okay, so Reb
Eliezer has, and Reb Eliezer probably also would say the מרגלים meraglim
won't get עולם הבא, olam haba, so which might have been that
previous line, might have been a Reb Eliezer line. Meaning, you understand
my point, that the מרגלים meraglim line could have been a Reb
Eliezer line. Reb Eliezer saying מרגלים meraglim don't have a חלק לעולם
הבא, chelek l'olam haba, קרח Korach isn't coming back up, but the
דור המדבר Dor HaMidbar does get a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam
haba. And Reb Akiva says like no, none of them get anything.
Was this Reb Eliezer that we were talking about before, Reb Akiva's
rebbe?
Yeah, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, and Reb Yehoshua, yeah, Reb Eliezer is
the about who?
Wasn't there a dispute about,
yeah, Reb Eliezer and Reb Yehoshua. Reb Eliezer is the has a
very narrow approach to who gets עולם הבא. olam haba.
Here he's more expansive.
Oh, that's true, that's a good point. Yeah, I guess when it
comes, right, you're right, good point, right, here he is דוקא dafka
more broader than he has been in the past when he was
dealing with חסידי אומות העולם Chasidei Umot HaOlam and when he was
dealing with whether we're going to do תשובה teshuvah or not. Okay.
תנו רבנן, tnu rabanan. דור המבול Dor HaMabul אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא. ein lahem chelek l'olam haba. וימח את כל היקום אשר על
פני האדמה. vayimach et kol hayekum asher al pnei ha'adama.
God wiped out all of
the everything that existed, that stood, וימח את כל היקום, vayimach et
kol hayekum, he wiped it out, he בעולם הזה, b'olam hazeh, וימחו
מן הארץ, vayimachu min ha'aretz, it was wiped out or whatever, eroded,
or wouldn't that be the word here, washed away, anyway, from the
land, לעולם הבא. l'olam haba. דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי
יהודה בן בתירה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer,
לא חיים ולא נדונים. lo chayim v'lo nidonim.
Not only did they not have a חלק לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam
haba, but this is the position in the משנה, Mishna, they don't
even get resurrected. שנאמר, She'ne'emar לא ידון רוחי באדם לעולם, lo yadon
ruchi b'adam l'olam, לא דין ולא רוח, lo din v'lo ruach,
not even a day of judgment. דבר אחר, davar acher, לא ידון
רוחי, lo yadon ruchi, שלא תהא נשמתם חוזרת לנדנה. she'lo tehei nishmasam
chozeret l'nadana.
The wind, the spirit, לא ידון רוחי, lo yadon ruchi, the רוח
ruach won't go back to its sheath, which is again another but
doing both the רוח ruach and the ידון yadon to say that
they won't be resurrected. They won't get their day in court. רבי
מנחם ברבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Menachem b'Rabbi Yose omer, אפילו בשעה שהקדוש
ברוך הוא מחזיר נשמות לפגרים מתים, afilu b'sha'ah she'hakadosh baruch hu machzir
nishamos l'fgarim mesim,
even when, notice that phrase, המחזיר נשמות לפגרים מתים, hamachzir nishamos l'fgarim
mesim, we have that as a ברכה, even when God restores the
soul to the dead carcasses at the time of תחיית המתים, t'chiyas
hametim, נשמתם קשה להם בגיהנום. nishmasam kasha lahem b'gehinnom.
Their soul is still suffering in גיהנום. gehinnom. I don't understand it
either, but it seems like you don't get a reprieve.
Sometimes there's guys in jail and waiting trial, and when he shows
up to court he's in a nice suit and he looks whatever,
right? So here I think what he's dealing with is the problem...
one minute, these רשעים, resha'im, they're going to get their תחיית המתים
t'chiyas hametim and there's going to be some יום הדין, yom hadin,
so what, they're going to get a few hours free from suffering
from גיהנום? gehinnom? No, somehow some part of their נשמה neshama is
still in גיהנום gehinnom suffering while they're also resurrected... I don't know
how you have that dual thing, maybe it's like a Horcrux or
something. But I don't really fully get it. I don't know if
your English explains it better, but I think he's just bothered how
do they get תחיית המתים t'chiyas hametim even for a brief time
and freed from the suffering for that period of time. So he
says their soul continues to suffer, קשה להם בגיהנום. kasha lahem b'gehinnom.
שנאמר, She'ne'emar
it says, תהרו חשש תלדו קש רוחכם אש תאכלכם. taharoo chashash teildoo
kash ruchachem esh tochalechem.
So you will become pregnant with... I don't remember the exact translation
of this verse, but anyway, a fire will consume your spirit. What
does it say there? Anything helpful?
תהרו חשש taharoo chashash is conceive of chaff, right,
it would say, and born of straw,
your fire will consume your spirit.
You just get the fire to light these things very easily.
Right, exactly. תנו רבנן. tnu rabanan.
This is suggesting the soul will destroy the body.
Oh, you mean קשה להם, kasha lahem, oh you mean what's the
word בגיהנום b'gehinnom then? You mean when the souls are back in
the bodies, the person's in tremendous pain.
That
was also with the earlier verse he was asking about an explanation.
It says at the time of the resurrection when the restoration of
the souls will bring the bodies of the righteous back to life,
the restoration of the souls of the wicked generation will not resurrect
the bodies but will merely increase the suffering of the bodies in
גיהנום. gehinnom.
Oh, that's an interesting
read, meaning that they'll be resurrected in גיהנום gehinnom and they won't
be resurrected on this earth and that... huh. That's an interesting read.
But anyway, but I hear the idea that it means that while
their soul is in the body, they're still suffering. The גיהנום gehinnom
phrase is a little interesting, unless it's really saying that they don't
even come up, that they stay in גיהנום gehinnom even at that
time. תנו רבנן. דור המבול לא נתגאו אלא בשביל טובה שהשפיע להם
הקדוש ברוך הוא. dor hamabul lo nitga'oo ela bishvil tovah she'hishpia lahem
hakadosh baruch hu. The problem was they had it too good. And
you have it too good, you start sinning and you're thinking that
you're a god and that... exactly. So they only had the arrogance
to act the way they did because God gave them so good.
וכתיב בהם, u'chtiv bahem, what does it say about them? Now we're
just going to quote a lot of פסוקים psukim from
איוב. Iyov. בתיהם שלום מפחד, bateihem shalom mipachad, their houses were free
from fear, ולא שבט אלוה עליהם, v'lo shevet eloha aleihem, they never
felt the rod of God, any suffering. וכתיב, u'chtiv, שורו עבר ולא
יגעיל, shoro avar v'lo yag'il, their oxen would go and not sort
of... whatever,
יגעיל, yag'il, anyway, suffer, not suffer, how do they translate it?
Not misdirect its seed.
Not
misdirect its seed? תפלט פרתו ולא תשכל. tapleit parato v'lo tishakeil. No,
that's the cow will give birth and not miscarry. וכתיב, u'chtiv, ישלחו
כצאן עויליהם, yishalchu kichon avileihem, they will send forth like the flock
their children, וילדיהם ירקדון, v'yaldeihem yerakedun, and their kids will dance. וכתיב,
u'chtiv, ישאו בתוף וכינור. yis'u b'tof v'chinor. Why all these פסוקים? psukim?
Because we want to illustrate how good they had it and that
this led to their downfall. And one can also imagine, I'm guessing
here, but there might have been a hidden critique of the
sort of Roman high life that they saw some of the wealthy
Romans engage in.
ויאמרו לאל סור ממנו ודעת דרכיך לא חפצנו, v'yomru la'eil sur mimenu
v'da'at derachecha lo chafatznu, which means that they were doing some sort
of had it good...
that's a good point, good פשט. pshat. It's a good פשט pshat
on the פסוקים. psukim. You're right.
דכתיב, Dichtiv, somebody said this just recently about the golden calf, that
they had it...
They had it too good. Yeah, right. Exactly. They're trying to understand
what led to the sinning, right? וכתוב V'chtiv
ובתוף וכינור ישמחו לקול עוגב uv'tof v'chinor yism'chu l'kol ugav playing all
these musical instruments, right? So they are like leaving the life... living
the life of Riley. וכתוב V'chtiv יבלו ימיהם בטוב yivlu y'meihem b'tov
their days were... were spent with all good things ושנותיהם בנעימים ushnoteihem
bin'imim right? They just were totally pampered like וכתוב V'chtiv וברגע שאול
יחתו uv'rega she'ol yeichatu and in a moment they descended into the
depths. Okay. והיא גרמה שם לאל V'hi garma sham l'E-l it was
because of all their goodness that led them to say to God,
סור ממנו Sur mimenu God, get away, leave us, who needs you?
ודעת דרכיך לא חפצנו V'da'at drachecha lo chafatznu we don't want to
know the way of serving God. מה שדי כי נעבדנו Ma Shaddai
ki na'avdennu who is God that we should serve him ומה נועיל
כי נפגע בו u'ma no'il ki nifga bo why should we entreat
God? Who needs God? We have it too good.
אמרו Amru בטובה שהשפעת להם בה הכעיסוני. B'tovah she'hishpata lahem ba hich'isuni.
I'm sorry, skipped a line. אמרו Amru כלום צריכין אנו לו אלא
לטיפה של גשמים. Klum tzrichin anu lo ela l'tipah shel geshaymim. Why
do we need God? The only thing we get from God... we
have so much wealth, where is... you know, we're as wealthy as
God. The only thing we get from God is we need it
to rain. Okay, that still comes from heaven. So יש לנו נהרות
ומעיינות שאנו מסתפקים בהם. yeish lanu neharot u'ma'ayanot she'anu mistafkim bahem. We
have enough rivers and wellsprings, who needs... who needs God? Similarly, I
mentioned before, the Gemara had a similar thing about who needs God's
light? We have this beautiful gold, that provides the light, remember that?
Anyway, אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, God says, בטובה
שהשפעתי להם בה הכעיסוני. B'tovah she'hishpati lahem ba hich'isuni. The very thing
that I, the... the goodness I poured out to them, this is
what they're angering me? They're throwing that in my face and they're
using that to reject me? And they're talking about the rain and
who needs the rain? Oh, you want to... you want to talk
about rain? I'll show you rain. Okay. בה אני דן אותם. Bah
ani dan otam. This is what they'll be judged with. שנאמר she'ne'emar
ואני הנני מביא את המבול מים. V'ani hineni meivi et hamabul mayim.
רבי יוסי אמר Rabbi Yossi amar דור המבול לא נתגאו אלא בשביל
גלגל העין Dor hamabul lo nitga'u ela bishvil galgal ha'ayin because of
their eye, it wasn't because of their wealth, right? It's an interesting
thing, like, let's speculate what led them astray. So the first thing
here is what led them astray was that they had it too
good, they had too much wealth and so on. No, what led
them astray was their eyes, right, right, right, is what they saw.
And this does pick up on... I've written about this, a theme
that sort of starts already going back to the first חטא. cheit.
You... you see something, you desire it, you take it. Okay. שנאמר
she'ne'emar ויקחו להם נשים מכל אשר בחרו. Vayikchu lahem nashim mikol asher
bacharu. Very relevant to all the stuff that's coming out in the
wake of Weinstein. I didn't even realize this, I was just reading
online the news last night and I... like, in the last week,
all these accusations of all from all different industries, right? It's not
just in Hollywood, it's like all these different people. Amazon, what's his
name, Wieseltier, all these people, like... everybody's coming forward, right? And exposing
what we always knew, you know, about how powerful men... that's what
it is... powerful men think they have the right to go ahead
and make use of women and treat you women as objects and
take... you know. And somebody's written about it also, like, about the...
they've done studies about the psychological, you know, the way power affects
your psychology. So you're not able to take... you know, judge risk
properly and you think... and your sense of entitlement and all these
types of things. Right? But like, since the very first, you know,
sin... creation, right? It's powerful men thinking that they can take women
and take whatever they
want. Okay. ולפיכך דנם במים. U'lephichach danam b'mayim.
Therefore God judged them with water, שדומה לגלגל העין, she'domeh l'galgal ha'ayin,
which is similar to the... like... like the eye. You know, I
guess it's the eye is like liquid and it's also like, you
know, a little opening, you know. That's why they call a מעיין
ma'ayan from עין, ayin, right? A little aperture, right? That's a sort
of... yeah.
Okay, so where was... שנאמר shene'emar נבקעו כל מעיינות תהום רבה. nivke'u
kol ma'aynot tehom rabba. Okay. וארובות השמים נפתחו. V'arubot hashamayim niftachu. So
מעיינות ma'aynot and עין. ayin. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan
דור המבול ברבה קלקלו וברבה נידונו. Dor hamabul b'rabba kilkelu u'v'rabba nidonu.
So now it's sort of showing the way the verses echoing the
word רבה. rabba. Okay. ברבה קלקלו B'rabba kilkelu שנאמר shene'emar וירא ה׳
כי רבה רעת האדם. vayar Hashem ki rabba ra'at ha'adam. Great was
the... was the evil of man. וברבה נידונו U'v'rabba nidonu and that
word was used to show their judgment שנאמר shene'emar כל מעיינות תהום
רבה. kol ma'aynot tehom rabba. Okay, the
great wellsprings. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan שלושה נשתיירו מהם. shlosha
nishtayru mehem. There's still three of those מעיינות, ma'aynot, of those hot
springs that still exist in the world. בלוע דגדר, Belu'a de-Gader, this
place Belu'a of Gader. חמי טבריה, Chamei Tverya, the hot springs of
Tiberias. וחמי v'chamei ועינא רבתי דבירם. ve-Einah Rabbati de-Biram. Okay, those three
places.
Do you know the other two?
We know Tiberias. I don't know. Is that in חמת? Hamat? Yeah,
גדר Gader right. Okay, כי השחית כל בשר את דרכו על הארץ
ki hish’hit kol basar et darko al ha-aretz off flesh had perverted
its way on the land. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yohanan, מלמד
שהרביעו בהמה על חיה וחיה על בהמה, melammed she-hirbi’u behemah al hayah
ve-hayah al behemah, they crossed animals to crossbreed, even of completely different,
not just different
species, but חיה hayah to בהמה behemah and so on, והכל על
אדם ואדם על הכל, ve-ha-kol al adam ve-adam al ha-kol, and human
beings with all of them. So that's the בשר basar is obviously
what they're picking up, flesh, like a sin of the flesh. And
השחית, hish’hit, so what does it mean to corrupt that? אמר רבי
אבא בר כהנא, Amar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana, וכולם חזרו חוץ מתשלומי.
ve-khullam hazaru hutz mi-tushlami.
All of the animals went back and humans to only copulating with
their own with their own מין, min, with their own species, except
for this תשלומי, tushlami, which is some bird that's supposed to be
very promiscuous. Okay. ויאמר אלהים לנח קץ כל בשר בא לפני. Va-yomer
Elohim le-Noach ketz kol basar ba le-fanai. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yohanan, בוא וראה כמה גדול כוחה של חמס. bo u-re’eh kammah gadol
koha shel hamas. Come see how great is the power of theft,
of חמס, hamas, or
presumably is how that's being read here, or violence, but okay, שהרי
דור המבול עברו על הכל. she-harei dor ha-mabbul averu al ha-kol.
They did all these horrific sins as we've just described, ולא נחתם
עליהם גזר דינם עד שפשטו ידיהם בגזל. ve-lo nehtam aleihem gezar dinam
ad she-pash’tu yedeihem be-gezel. But it was only until they got to
theft in the end. Theft is just continuing that point about just
taking whatever you want, you're just seeing and desiring and taking. שנאמר
כי מלאה הארץ חמס מפניהם והנני משחיתם את הארץ. shenne’emar ki male’ah
ha-aretz hamas mi-peneihem ve-hinneni mash’hitam et ha-aretz.
That is the straw that broke the back. וכתיב החמס קם למטה
רשע. ve-khtiv ha-hamas kam le-matteh rasha. Hamas rises up for a rod
for the wicked. לא מהם ולא מהמונם ולא מהמהם ולא נה בהם.
lo me-hem ve-lo me-hamonam ve-lo me-hemahem ve-lo noah ba-hem. Not amongst them,
not of their masses, not of their...
I don't know what that means, and there
is no eulogizing, no wailing for them. Okay, אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar
Rabbi Eleazar, that's a פסוק. מלמד שזקף את עצמו כמקל, melammed she-zakaf
et atzmo ke-makkal, and the חמס hamas
stood up like a rod, והחמס עמד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, ve-ha-hamas
amad lifnei ha-kadosh barukh hu, stood before God, ואמר לפניו רבונו של
עולם, ve-amar lefanav ribbono shel olam, Master of the Universe, לא מהם,
lo me-hem, they've sinned so much I guess that even חמס hamas
got fed up. Okay, and God said לא מהם, lo me-hem, I
don't want them, ולא מהמונם ולא מהמהם ולא נה בהם. ve-lo me-hamonam
ve-lo me-hemahem ve-lo noah ba-hem. Okay, whatever all that means. Okay. ואף
על נח נחתם גזר דין. ve-af al Noach nehtam gezar din. שנאמר
ולא נח בהם shenne’emar ve-lo noah ba-hem is the גרסא. girsa. And
we're going to say that in a minute. Like נה noh or
whatever, נהי, nehi, whatever which is wailing is here being read as
נח. Noach. Noah wasn't so righteous. Maybe or maybe he deserved... we'll
get to it. Or maybe he deserved to be wiped out the
same way the whole earth deserved to be wiped out even if
his own he was a צדיק, tzaddik, but sometimes that's not good
enough when there's
a communal tragedy, communal punishment, okay, right, which is a theme in
חז"ל, Hazal, right? When things happen at a national scale or communal
scale, people don't get necessarily judged and protected on their individual basis.
Okay, so תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, tana de-vei Rabbi Yishmael, אף על
נח נחתך גזר דין. af al Noach nehtakh gezar din.
Even Noah was sort of the judgment was ruled against him, אלא
שמצא חן בעיני השם. ella she-matza hen be-einei Hashem. So this actually
seems like even in terms of at a personal level, technically speaking,
he was deserving to be wiped out, but for some reason God
said he found favor in God's eyes, like it was undeserved, special
חן. hen. Okay, שנאמר ניחמתי כי עשיתים ונח. shenne’emar nihamti ki asitim
ve-Noach. I have
I regret that I have made them and Noah, and that I
have made... oh. And then מצא חן בעיני השם. matza hen be-einei
Hashem. But nevertheless Noah is מצא חן. matza hen. Okay. וינחם השם
כי עשה את האדם בארץ. Va-yinnahem Hashem ki asah et ha-adam ba-aretz.
כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi amar, אמר הקדוש
ברוך הוא, amar ha-Kadosh Barukh Hu, יפה עשיתי שהתקנתי להם קברות בארץ.
yafeh asiti she-hitkanti lahem kevarot ba-aretz.
I did good that I made graves for them in the ground
because God וינחם, va-yinnahem, God was consoled, God felt comforted by the
fact כי עשה את האדם בארץ, ki asah et ha-adam ba-aretz, he
made it that man could be buried in the ground. מאי משמע?
mai mashma? כתיב הכא וינחם השם, ktiv hacha va-yinnahem Hashem, כתיב התם
וינחם אותם וידבר על לבם. ktiv hatam va-yennahem otam va-yedabber al libbam.
Joseph comforted them. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amrei,
just showing that the word וינחם va-yinnahem could mean comfort. Okay, to
mean as opposed to regret. God was comforted that he made... איכא
דאמרי, Ika de-amrei, some say, לא יפה עשיתי שהתקנתי להם קברות בארץ.
lo yafeh asiti she-hitkanti lahem kevarot ba-aretz. I did not do good
that I made for them graves in the ground. כתיב הכא וינחם,
ktiv hacha va-yinnahem, וכתיב התם וינחם השם על הרעה. u-khtiv hatam va-yinnahem
Hashem al ha-ra’ah. I regret that I made graves. Now, what difference
does it make whether you made graves for them or you didn't
make graves for them? So רש"י Rashi says שאיבדתי דרך רשעים כזה.
she-ibbadeti derekh resha'im ka-zeh. It means whether he was comforted or whether
he regretted actually destroying them. So it's not really about the graves.
The graves is really a metaphor of that he says it's good
that I wipe them out or it's not good that I wipe
them out, I should have actually given them another chance. Okay, that's
at least the way רש"י Rashi is reading it. Okay. But of
course that's saying it before he actually wiped them out. So it
seems that it more has to do with the fact about whether
as a result of being when they die are they going to
be their bodies are going to sink... I don't know how to
explain it, but it doesn't seem like the גמרא Gemara is discussing
whether he's comforted or regretted his decision to kill them, it's whether
it's a good thing or a bad thing that their bodies sink
into the ground. Down and get buried in the earth. But I
don't know why that should matter one way or the other.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
אלו
תולדות נח נח איש צדיק תמים היה בדורותיו Aleu Toldot Noach Noach
Ish Tzaddik Tamim Hayah Bedorotav אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan
בדורותיו Bedorotav obviously now what we're doing is we're just focusing on
Noah. Okay. בדורותיו Bedorotav ולא בדורות אחרים. Velo Bedorot Acheirim. This is
the classic debate. For his generation he was righteous, not in others.
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish אמר בדורותיו Amar Bedorotav כל שכן בדורות אחרים.
Kolkhe Sh'ken Bedorot Acheirim. If he could be righteous in that generation,
to make it in you here, you could make it anywhere. You
could be okay. אמר רב חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina משל דרבי יוחנן
למה הדבר דומה. Mashal Derabbi Yochanan Lemah Hadavar Domeh. What's Rabbi Yochanan
like? לכביץ של יין שמונח במרתף של חומץ. Lekhavitz Shel Yayin Shemunach
B'martef Shel Chometz. If you had a wine barrel in middle of
all this vinegar. במקומו ריחו נודף. Bimkomo Reicho Nodeif.
So you can smell it really smells good with all that bad
smell around. שלא במקומו אין ריחו נודף. Shelo Bimkomo Ein Reicho Nodeif.
Not in its place, yeah okay, it wouldn't be such a such
a big deal. Of course the imagery of the vinegar is significant
because I think when you put it around vinegar it causes the
wine to turn to vinegar faster. So he's like not denying the
power of the fact that Noach did resist, like it seems like
everybody is agreeing to the same phenomenon. Noach had the ability to
resist the powerful evil influences of his generation, but at the end
of the day, he was not the world's greatest צדיק Tzaddik judged
based on like other people who didn't have to resist those influences.
Okay, so Rabbi Yochanan is like emphasizing the negative. His actual objective
level of צדקות Tzidkus wasn't so great, but he's not denying the
fact that he resisted all of this vinegar around him. One minute,
and the other one is sort of saying look let's look at
it theoretically. And maybe his objective level was only a six, but
had he lived in a different generation he would have become a
ten. So you shouldn't judge him based on the fact that he
was a six. Okay. אמר רבי אושעיא Amar Rabbi Oshea משל דרייש
לקיש למה הדבר דומה. Mashal Direish Lakish Lemah Hadavar Domeh. What's Resh
Lakish like? לצלוחית של פלייטון Litzlochit Shel Palyatin פלייטון Palyatom like a
little jar of like of of perfume, perfumer's, שמונח במקום הטינופת Shemunach
Bimkom Hatinoifet
which is in a smelly place. במקומו ריחו נודף Bimkomo Reicho Nodeif
and it was able to like cover up the icky smell, right
that's what you do, you spray some perfume or whatever, but you
don't get to smell you don't because of the icky smell around
you don't really smell the power of the perfume it just covers
it up. Okay. כל שכן במקום הבשמים Kolkhe Sh'ken Bimkom Habisomim
certainly if it was in a more aromatic place you would really
smell how beautiful it was. So this seems to say maybe it's
actually saying whatever anyway, so because he but I don't exactly get
the metaphor I must say because because of the evil people around
him that made you not appreciate Noach as much like I don't
exactly get the metaphor.
Because of himself in the sense of Resh Lakish coming from being
a robber and like his whole background so what it's like to
be a good guy among bad guys
as opposed
to being a good guy among good guys.
That's a nice that's interesting. That's interesting or Resh Lakish is giving
the yeah that's a good point you know maybe Resh Lakish is
sort of like reflecting the fact that that he also had like
a challenging background and what could I have been if I had
a different type of an upbringing. That's an interesting insight. Okay. So
now the גמרא says like this. וימח את כל היקום אשר על
פני האדמה Vayimach Et Kol Hayekum Asher Al Pnei Haadamah אם אדם
חטא בהמה מה חטאה Im Adam Chata Behemah Mah Chat'ah
if the humans sinned what did the animals sin. תנא משום רבי
יהושע בן קרחה Tana Mishum Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Karchah משל לאדם שעשה
חופה לבנו Mashal Leadam Sheasah Chuppah Livno he made a whole wedding
feast for his son והתקין מכל מיני סעודה Vehitkin Mikol Minei Seudah
and he made all these great of great delicacies. לימים מת בנו
Leyamim Meit Beno
and then his son died presumably even before the wedding. עמד ופיזר
חופתו Amad Upizeir Chuppato he went and he like just destroyed
scattered all of the חופה Chuppah and all the food and threw
it all out. אמר כלום עשיתי אלא בשביל בני Amar Klum Asiti
Ela Bishvil Beni I only made this for my son's wedding. עכשיו
שמת חופה למה לי Achshav Shemeit Chuppah Lamah Li he's dead so
there's no purpose of all of this. אף הקדוש ברוך הוא אמר
כלום בראתי בהמה וחיה אלא בשביל אדם Af Hakadosh Baruch Hu Amar
Klum Barati Behemah Vechayah Ela Bishvil Adam classic Rabbinic sort of theology.
All animal like based on the six days of creation everything was
created just to serve humans. עכשיו שאדם חוטא בהמה וחיה למה לי
Achshav Sheadam Chote Behemah Vechayah Lamah Li if I'm going to destroy
the humans so I have no need for anything I gotta start
all over again. מכל אשר בחרבה מתו Mikol Asher Becharavah Meitu
everything on the dry land died ולא דגים שבים Velo Dagim Shebayam
only stuff on the dry land not the fish in the sea.
Okay. ואומר דרש רבי יוסי דמן קיסרי מה דכתיב Veomer Darash Rabbi
Yosi Demin Keisari Mah Dichshiv what's meant by the verse קל הוא
על פני מים תוקלל חלקתם בארץ Kal Hu Al Pnei Mayim Tukolal
Chelkatam Baaretz
light is it on the water their portion should be cursed on
the earth. מלמד שהיה נח הצדיק מוכיח בהם ואומר להם Melamed Shehayah
Noach HaTzaddik Mochiach Bahem V'omer Lahem so we're done with the fish.
Presumably the reason the fish weren't punished was because they didn't תשחיתו
Tishchitu fish don't copulate directly right they lay their eggs and then
other fish isn't that how it
works anyway. Okay. מלמד שהיה נח הצדיק Melamed Shehayah Noach HaTzaddik Noach
the righteous. מוכיח בהם ואומר להם Mochiach Bahem V'omer Lahem
עשו תשובה עשו תשובה Asu Tshuvah Asu Tshuvah do
תשובה Tshuvah do תשובה Tshuvah ואם לאו הקדוש ברוך הוא מביא עליכם
את המבול V'im Lav Hakadosh Baruch Hu Meivi Aleichem Et Hamabbul if
not God will bring the flood. ומקפה נבלתכם על המים Umakfe nivlatcham
al hamayim and it will cause your corpses to float on the
on the water כזיקין kizikin like a like a flasks שנאמר shene'emar
קלו על פני המים kalu al pnei hamayim according to this פסוק
it'll be like something light floating on the water. ולא עוד אלא
שלא קמו מהם קללה לכל באי עולם Velo od ela shelo qamu
mehem klala lechol ba'ei olam all future generations will curse, you know,
will use you as a curse שנאמר תקולל חלקתם בארץ tekulel chelkatam
ba'aretz your portion will be as a curse on the land. לא
יפנה דרך כרמים Lo yifne derech kramim not turn to the way
of vineyards, we'll talk about what that means. מלמד שהיו מפנים דרך
כרמים Melamed shehayu mafnim derech kramim they would turn to the way
of vineyards, that's not a clear what that means, we'll get back
to that in a minute. אמרו לו Amru lo they said to
him ומי מעכב? umi me'akev? So if that's really true that God
wants to kill us, what's stopping him from doing it now? אמר
להם Amar lahem פרה אחת יש לי para achas yesh li or
what יש לו yesh lo whatever להוציא מהם lehotzi mehem or whatever.
God is talking anyway, God still has one person he's trying to
save, meaning not just נח, Noach, but the point is that מתושלח,
Metushelach, right if you do the dates מתושלח Metushelach dies exactly at
the same year of the מבול. mabul. So the version, the idea
is that God wanted to wait for מתושלח הצדיק Metushelach hatzadik to
die in this version he's a צדיק, tzadik, whatever, in order to
be able to bring the מבול mabul when they were all wicked.
אם כן Im ken לא נפנה דרך כרמים, lo nifne derech kramim,
ah they said, so if there's time or whatever we don't believe
you exactly, we're not going to, there's a little unclear what this
means, but anyway we're not going to turn away from the path
of the vineyards. So רש"י says the path of the vineyards means
like as opposed to the straight and the narrow, the path of
the vineyards, like I don't know maybe there's temptations there's all the
grapes there but there's also the thorns and the thistles. So somehow
it's a metaphor to say, ah, so then we don't believe you,
we're just going to keep on going off the דרך. derech. Okay,
דרש רבא darash Rava מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv what's meant by the
verse? Read it a little bit more. לפיד בוז לעשתות שאנן נכון
למועדי Lapid buz le'ashtut sha'anan nachon lemo'adai a a blade of despoiling
for לעשתות le'ashtut which רש"י says means those that are sort of
in, you know, have it good, for the
for
the comfortable a a blade is ready for my
appointed time. למועדי רגל Lemo'adei regel for the appointed time of the
leg, whatever that means. מלמד שהיה נח הצדיק מוכיח אותם Melamed shehaya
Noach hatzadik mochiach otam Noach would would give them מוסר ואמר להם
ve'amar lahem
דברים שהם קשים כלפידים devarim shehem kashim kelapidim he would tell them
things that were as harsh as like as a blade of a
sword. והיו מבזים אותם Vehayu mevazim otam so that was בוז buz
they would you know they would denigrate him, they would despise him.
אמרו לו Amru lo פחח pachach you don't know what you're talking
about, you're an idiot. אמרו לו Amru lo זקן תיבה זו למה?
teva zu lama? Hey hey old guy, what are what are you
building this box for? אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא מביא עליכם את
המבול Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu mevi aleichem et hamabul God's going
to bring the flood. אמרו Amru מבול של מה? mabul shel ma?
What type of a flood? אם מבול של אש Im mabul shel
esh if it's a flood of fire, יש לנו דבר אחר ואליתא
שמה yesh lanu davar acher ve'alita shema we have something that's called
אליתא Alita that protects us from fire. Okay, I have no idea
what it is. ואם של מים הוא Ve'im shel mayim hu if
it's a flood of water מביא mevi אם מן הארץ הוא מביא
im min ha'aretz hu mevi if it's going to be that the
flood is going to rise up from the ground, יש לנו עששיות
של ברזל yesh lanu ashashiyot shel barzel we have like these iron
types of protectors שאנו מחפים בהם את הארץ she'anu mechafim bahem et
ha'aretz we'll just you know we'll just cover the ground with like
iron plates of iron and it'll stop the water from rising up.
ואם מן השמים הוא מביא Ve'im min hashamayim hu mevi and if
it's going to be a rain from heaven, יש לנו דבר ועקש
שמה yesh lanu davar ve'akash shemo ואמרי לה ve'amrei la עקש שמה
akash shemo
עקב akav or עקש akash whatever it is and that's somehow going
to protect us. We're going to build, build whatever, building some type
of a dome, we got it covered. אמר להם Amar lahem הוא
מביא מבין עקבי רגליכם hu mevi mibein ikvei ragleichem God can do
anything, He can even bring from between your, you know, from between
your your heels. Okay, שנאמר נכון למועדי רגל nachon lemo'adei regel ready
for those for between the heel, not the the most sensitive point.
Oh, maybe the most sensitive point, whatever the yeah.
Okay, right, it could just mean like He'll just bring it out
of your bodies or something, but this also רש"י has another read
which is going to get to the next point which is talking
specifically about semen. Okay, He could even drown you in your own
semen if He wanted to. And the עקב akev is often used
as a metaphor for the genital area and so on. תניא Tanya
מימי המבול mei hamabul it's done in a ברייתא Braisa the waters
of the מבול mabul קשים כשכבת זרע kashim keshichvat zera were like
as you know as thick and as hot and as whatever
as
as semen.
Okay, שנאמר נכון nachon ready למועדי רגל lemo'adei regel for those of
like the appointed time of the leg or of the foot. אמר
רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda ברותחין קלקלו berotchin kilkelu they sinned, what?
I mean semen is usually for creation.
Oh,
that's a good point. Right, so a semen, that's a good point,
semen is for creation and water also, water brings life and water
is destroying. I haven't thought about that the same as about semen,
but also obviously this is getting back to how they sexual sins,
right? Which is now how the גמרא is going to tie it
in.
Okay, ברותחין קלקלו berotchin kilkelu they sinned with this hot liquid semen,
בעבירה ba'avera וברותחין נידונו uverotchin nidunu and by it it was judged.
כתיב הכא Ktiv hacha וישכו
המים vayashoku hamayim the waters abated, כתיב התם ktiv hatam וחמת המלך
שככה vechamat hamelech shachacha the anger of the king abated, but it's
something... Now based on the גמרא *Gemara* we read, you would have
thought that the sin of the semen means the breeding with other
species, right? That's what we've been describing, right? That they bred with
all other animals and so on. But this גמרא *Gemara* is often
read, although I don't think it's saying it here, but the גמרא
*Gemara* is often read to mean שכבת זרע לבטלה *shichvas zera levatala*,
the sin of masturbating and of ejaculating like in a non-you-know context
of sexual intercourse, right, you know, so, so that, so this is
often brought in terms of this and that's important for questions about
like how bad is the sin of masturbating or whatever. So some
say what do you mean that was the reason why the whole
דור המבול *dor hamabul* was wiped out, was that they were all
masturbators. Okay, but that's not in our גמרא *Gemara*. I mean the
גמרא *Gemara* says that they sinned sexually, but it seems like it
was a different sin. Alright, anyway, it was the cross-breeding. Let's just
read one more thing and then we'll wrap up for today. ויהי
לשבעת הימים *Vayehi l'shivas hayamim*, seven days. ומי המבול היו על הארץ
*U'mei hamabul hayu al ha'aretz*. למה המתין שבעת הימים *Lama himtin shivas
hayamim*? Why did God have to wait seven days once it was
time? אמר רב אלו ימי אבלו של מתושלח *Amar Rav eilu yemei
eivlo shel Mesushelach*. Right, that was sort of what we alluded to
before. Okay, this is the period of the mourning of מתושלח *Mesushelach*.
ללמדך שהספדן של צדיקים מעכבין את הפורענות *Lelamedcha she'hespadan shel tzaddikim me'akvin
es hapur'anos*. Even just the period of eulogizing the righteous holds back
bad things from happening לבוא *lavo*. דבר אחר לשבעה ששינה להם הקדוש
ברוך הוא סדרי בראשית *Davar acher l'shivah she'shinah lahem HaKadosh Baruch Hu
sidrei Bereishis*. God reversed the ways of creation. שבעת ימים *Shiv'as yamim*
echoes the days of creation and like there's a lot of good
textual reading of the נח *Noach* story where you see it's a
reversing and a new creation story, right, just think about how creation
is about separating the water and the earth and this is mixing
of the water and the earth, right, they come out of the
תיבה *teivah*, God says פרו ורבו *p'ru u'revu*, whatever. Anyway, so it
is a whole new reversing and re-creation story. שהייתה חמה יוצאת ממערב
ושוקעת במזרח *She'haysa chamah yotzeis mimarav v'shoka'as bamizrach*. And the גמרא *Gemara*
describes it very, very whatever, you know, with this image, the sun
would rise in the west and set in the east. דבר אחר
*Davar acher*, another explanation of seven days. שקבע להם הקדוש ברוך הוא
זמן גדול ואחר כך זמן קטן *She'kava lahem HaKadosh Baruch Hu zman
gadol v'achar kach zman katan*. First God gets gave them 120 years
to do תשובה *teshuvah*, then God says okay, seven days. Okay, by
the way, that's what works for me. If you tell me something
is due in like a month, I am never going to get
it done. If it's due in like today, two days, that's when
I get it done. Okay. You got a week to do תשובה
*teshuvah*. Oh, a week, I better, I'm going to work on it.
Okay. דבר אחר לשבעת הימים שהטעימם מעין עולם הבא *Davar acher l'shivas
hayamim she'hit'imam me'ein olam haba*. So I don't know how the שבעת
הימים *shivas hayamim*, but like שבת *Shabbos* is the like עולם הבא
*olam haba*. Anyway, they got a taste of what the future world
would be כדי שידעו מה טובה מנעו מהם *kedei she'yedu mah tovah
manu mei'hem*. Okay, that they should know what the you know what
good that they had held back from themselves because of, because of
their sin. Alright, I guess we will end we will end here
pick up tomorrow.
Alright, tomorrow's going to be my last day for a while. I'm
going to guess I'll have to talk really fast. They won't want
you to stop. I'll, I'll try to be here really like early
right on time tomorrow seven, let's try to start exactly on time
so we definitely have some.